Finding Aid for Citizens Opposed to Super Sewer Records 1968-1976
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Citizens Opposed to Super Sewer records 1968-1976
Citizens Opposed to Super Sewer.
1 linear ft.
Organization formed to oppose construction of a sewer interceptor for Oakland, Macomb, Washtenaw and Wayne counties, Michigan. Office records, clippings, and topical files.
85102 Bt 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was donated by William Pollard (donor no. 6415 ) in 1980.
The record group is open for research.
In 1967 the Detroit Metropolitan Area Regional Planning Commission (later a part of the Southeast Michigan Council of Governments-SEMCOG) approved the construction of a single sewer interceptor collecting sewage from parts of Oakland, Macomb, Washtenaw and Wayne counties. "super sewer," as the project was popularly known, involved over 90 miles of sewer construction, ending at Pointe Mouillée where a massive plant was planned to treat the waste water before it entered Lake Erie.
Opposition to the project slowly began to grow. By 1973 "super sewer" had become a major political question within southeastern Michigan. Opposition was based on three arguments. The cost effectiveness of building one large project compared to upgrading already existing local sewage facilities was questioned. The ecological effect of the project, particularly its effect on the rate of water flow in the Huron River, became a matter of concern. Finally, political opposition, based on the perception that super sewer benefited Wayne County and the city of Detroit to the detriment of other parts of the region, emerged.
Citizens Opposed to Super Sewer (COSS) was one of the groups which fought the construction of the project. A voluntary organization, COSS was most active in 1973. Its membership was composed primarily of non-Wayne County residents.
The records created by COSS consists of office records of the organization, primarily generated in 1973 and 1974. The files include correspondence, statements, memoranda, and collected information.
Subjects:
Citizens Opposed to Super Sewer.; Sewerage--Michigan.; Citizens' associations--Michigan.
- Office material
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - 1968 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1973
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Department of Natural Resources (Box 1)
    - Environmental Protection Agency/Corps of Engineers (Box 1)
    - Fundraising (Box 1)
    - Letters to the editor (Box 1)
    - Michigan Water Resources Commission (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Modeling and Simulation of Lakes and Impoundments (Box 1)
    - Names (Box 1)
    - Notes (Box 1)
    - Pointe Mouillée Waterfowlers Association (Box 1)
    - Speaking requests (Box 1)
  - 1974, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1975 (Box 1)
  - 1976 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)